[SQUEAKING]
[RUSTLING]
[CLICKING]
GIAN PAOLO BERETTA:
OK, good morning.
So we started talking about
multi-component systems,
mixtures.
And our program is
that at the beginning,
we try to see when
it is possible
to infer the properties of a
mixture as much as possible
from the properties of
the pure components.
And so we are in the process of
defining some ideal situations
in which this is possible,
which as we said,
is a good start in
our modeling efforts.
It's like a reference
sample situation
in which we do not need to
add experimental data to model
our mixtures.
But then we will find that in
practice, the ideal situation
is really only a
limiting situation, which
is not fulfilled by any real
mixture, except in some limits.
Nevertheless, we gain
a lot of information
by just looking at
ideal situations.
So we have defined
these partial properties
that are derivatives or
functions of the chemical
potentials.
For example, the partial
entropy of the constituent
in the mixture, which is
a function of t, p, and y.
We will have to be careful
in distinguishing well
between the partial entropy of
the constituent in the mixture
and the s double i
tp, which is going
to be-- which is the specific
property, the specific entropy,
of pure component i when
at the same temperature
and pressure of the mixture.
We will see that they
are somehow related
and the difference
is measurable.
So we have to pay a lot of
attention to the subscripts.
Like, so a single subscript
is a partial property
for the mixture.
Double subscript is specific
property of the pure component.
And then we define
the partial volume,
which is another derivative
of the chemical potential
once we know the
chemical potentials
as a function of temperature,
pressure, and composition.
We define the partial energy.
And also, we define
the partial enthalpy.
And let me just stress this one.
If you have the expression
for the chemical potential
and you divide it
by the temperature,
and take the derivative not with
respect to t, but with respect
to the inverse of
the temperature,
then you get the
partial enthalpy.
This formula will come
out a while often.
And also, this one, which I
better write here on the board,
we can write it this way.
OK, so we can say that--
we can see that from
this relation here,
we can see that the
chemical potential can be--
of the component
in the mixture can
be written as this linear
combination, enthalpy
minus ts, which
essentially is also
equal to the Gibbs free energy.
So this is also equal to the
partial Gibbs free energy.
And in fact, the derivative of g
with respect to ni, with respect
fixed t and p, and the
other constituents,
that's the definition of the
chemical potential in terms
of the Gibbs free energy.
But it's also-- you could
also call it by analogy
with these definitions,
the partial Gibbs
free energy of the
constituent in the mixture.
So in other words, we're saying
that the chemical potential
can be interpreted itself
as a partial property.
It's the partial
Gibbs free energy
of the constituent
in the mixture.
And the reason why we call
these properties partial
is because they
contribute to building up
the property of the mixture
by simple multiplication
with their amounts.
And each-- and you can do this
for entropy, volume, energy,
the free energies, the enthalpy.
They are all-- they all
have the same structure.
Of course, now, we are-- we
forget the small systems,
and we focus on large systems.
So this is the right-hand
side, the highlighted formulas,
because for small
systems, we will
have also to some
contributions that
correct this expression in
terms of the Euler free energy.
OK, so how do we measure
these partial properties?
And here's the setup.
We take a mixture with
a given composition,
in stable equilibrium of course.
I know I'm not repeating
it often enough,
but we are concentrating
our attention now
on the stable equilibrium state.
And so we take a mixture
with some given composition
at a stable equilibrium state,
the temperature and pressure p.
And we put it in
mutual equilibrium
with a thermal reservoir
of the kind that
can exchange also volume.
So you have also the
pressure equality
as a condition for mutual
equilibrium between your mixture
and the reservoir.
Then we take a little
bit of pure component i,
and we add it to the mixture.
And we wait until the
mixture goes again
to mutual equilibrium with
that thermal reservoir.
OK, so this is a
mixing process in which
we add a small amount of
one of the components.
And then since we can measure
properties of systems,
for example, let me
take the enthalpy.
And so let me measure the
difference between the enthalpy
of the mixture in
this final state
and the enthalpy of the
composite system of the mixture
plus the pure component
in the initial state.
OK, so this is for the
mixture in the final state.
The amounts are the same, but
the amount for the constituent i
is n plus dn.
This is the initial where in
the mixture, I just have ni
and the dni is separate
from the mixture.
So it contributes with its own--
to the enthalpy of
the pure constituent
through its specific property
of the pure component.
And notice that usually, as I
said several times, enthalpy
is not an additive property.
But if you're looking at systems
that are at the same temp--
pressure, then
enthalpy is additive.
And therefore, the enthalpy
of the composite of these two
subsystems is equal to the
sum of the two enthalpies,
like we do here, the sum of
the enthalpy of the mixture,
plus the enthalpy of
the pure component.
OK, now if we take
this and divide it
by the amount of
constituent i that we
have added to the mixture,
that defines the change
in the enthalpy due to
the addition of that
amount of a small amount
of that component.
And of course, the n is
supposed to be small.
So we're taking the
limit of this, which is--
which can be viewed as an
incremental product, at least
the part with the
capital H. It's
a partial derivative of
capital H with respect to ni.
And then there is this
additional contribution
of the separate pure
component that we have added,
which since I divided--
I'm dividing by dni
adds, but with the minus
sign, a contribution here.
Now, we recognize
that this derivative
is exactly what we defined
as the partial enthalpy
of the constituent in the
mixture in the previous slide.
So here, we have the difference
between the partial enthalpy
and the specific enthalpy
of pure component
at the same [INAUDIBLE]
of the mixture.
This is what we
call the enthalpy
of isothermobaric mixing.
Tp stands for
isothermal and isobaric
because we are doing
this in a fixed T
and p imposed by the reservoir.
This can be measured.
Enthalpy in a process
like this is essentially,
if you make the
energy balance, this
is essentially
the heat exchanged
with the thermal reservoir.
So you measure it
with a calorimeter.
So that means that since you can
measure this with a calorimeter
and you know the properties
of pure substances,
then you have measured
the partial enthalpy
of the component in the mixture.
And this doesn't require
any particular assumptions
about the mixture being
ideal or non-ideal.
We actually haven't even
defined yet what ideal means.
It's simply a tool, a
method, with which people
measure properties of mixtures.
And what we have done
here for the enthalpy
can be repeated the same way.
So I'm not repeating
it here, but to define
the volume of mixing,
so it's the difference
between the partial volume
and the specific volume
at the same t and p,
the energy of mixing
and the entropy of mixing.
And these are all things
that you can measure
by energy and entropy balances.
So these are ways in which
you can characterize.
OK, this is a--
oops, sorry.
Yeah, there is an
extra character there.
OK.
All right.
So now, let's use
that equation, which
I've written up
there on the board
and substitute the expression of
the partial enthalpy as a hii.
So the specific enthalpy
of the pure component
times the enthalpy of mixing.
And the same for the
entropy, s partial.
We can write it as s specific
of the pure component
times the entropy of
isothermobaric mixing.
All right, so then,
we recognize that also
for the pure substance, h minus
ts is the chemical potential.
So this gives us a relation
for the chemical potential,
the component in
the mixture in terms
of the chemical potential
of the pure component
at the same temperature and
pressure of the mixture,
plus the enthalpy of
mixing minus t times
the entropy of mixing.
And at this stage, we
should also remember that
by the definition of partial
pressures of components
in a mixture.
You recall that that is
defined by the condition
of mutual equilibrium across
a membrane, permeable only,
to constituent i.
So at that mutual equilibrium
across the membrane,
you have equality of
chemical potentials.
So the chemical potential of
a constituent in the mixture
is also equal to the
chemical potential.
And here, there is
also another mistake.
This should be a double i.
This is the chemical
potential of a pure component
on the other side of the
semi-permeable membrane.
And therefore, yes.
At the same temperature
of the mixture,
but at a pressure which is what
we call the partial pressure.
So again, here, I cut and
paste, makes errors propagate.
So this should be
double i and double i.
OK, so the-- we are now
taking this last equality
and putting in evidence
the difference.
And so taking essentially this
term to the right-hand side.
So I have the chemical
potential difference
evaluated between the
pressure-- the partial pressure
and the pressure of the
mixture, pii minus p.
Now here, we have already
proved in a previous slide,
maybe we can just
remind ourselves
of how they got here, that--
so we are having that
new double i pii--
I'm sorry, at t and pii minus
[INAUDIBLE] double i tp.
OK, you see, I'm--
if I have a function of x, And
the difference of a function
evaluated at two
different points,
I can always write by the
integral calculus equation
that this is equal to
the integral from x2
to x1 of the derivative
of that function.
Let's call it--
And this x double prime is a
dummy variable of integration.
OK, so these, you can
write for any function.
So here, we apply this theorem.
So this x2 is p, x1 is
p1ii, and the derivative
we have to put here is the
partial derivative with respect
to p of what?
Of the chemical potential
of the pure component
while the other
variables are tp--
I'm sorry, t.
And this is to be evaluated at
the value of the dummy variable,
so at p double
prime, and integrated
over the dummy variable.
But if you look up
the many equations
that we have derived also
for the pure substance,
this derivative is
the specific volume.
So this becomes the specific
volume of the pure component
evaluated at temperature t
and at the dummy pressure p
of integration p double prime.
OK, all right.
So that explains
this integral here.
But above, we've seen that
this difference in chemical
potentials is equal to the delta
h mix minus ts delta s mix.
OK, now look at this volume.
If I have an ideal
gas, and if I can--
my substance i behaves according
to the ideal gas relation,
the specific volume can
be written as rt over p.
And the pressure that we should
evaluate is p that is here.
So it's p double prime.
And so when I do this
integral, rt goes outside
because I'm integrating
over p, p double prime.
And the integral of 1
over p is the logarithm.
So that gives me the formula
rt log of pii over p.
And that's for the gas.
If instead I have
a liquid and I can
use the incompressible
liquid model for which
the specific volume vii
is approximately constant,
meaning independent of
temperature and pressure,
well, if it is a constant,
it goes out of the integral.
And then this becomes
the specific volume times
pii minus p.
And here in the
slide, I just switch
because the pressure
is usually greater
than the partial pressure.
So I put this difference
in parentheses
and then I pick up a minus
sign on the other side.
OK, so this formula will
be useful in a moment.
And again, we see that
there is a relation
between the partial pressures,
very explicit relations in terms
of the enthalpy and the entropy
of isothermobaric mixing.
So this is a way in which you
can measure partial pressures
because you can
measure the properties
of isothermobaric mixing.
For example, here, I want to
sort of point you to a couple
of references, which if you go
and take a look, and they'll--
a huge literature,
so a huge community
that over many
decades, or perhaps
over more than a
century, have been
measuring properties this way.
And they're still doing it
because the applications
are growing.
For example, this is
an experimental paper
where they collect--
they measure the enthalpy
of isothermobaric mixing
of liquids.
And these liquids are molten
salts that, as you may know,
are used in various
applications,
including solar thermal
applications in those collectors
with mirrors that want to
achieve high temperatures.
The molten salts allow stable
also at very high temperatures.
And therefore,
using these fluids,
you can collect solar
energy at high temperatures
up to maybe 600 Celsius.
But of course, molten salts are
used also in nuclear engineering
and in processing industries
for producing materials
that are useful for all
sorts of applications,
from electronics to magnets.
OK, so this is for--
so this is a
reference in which you
can see how people measure
and then try to correlate.
So there is also a
number of correlations,
which go under the names of the
inventors of the correlations,
that do good jobs in
determining these effects.
You see, here, the gray
molecule, cesium ion,
is sort of the solvent.
It's like the prevailing,
or the common substance
of these mixtures.
And then they keep changing
the other substance.
So it's actually
not only for dilute,
it's for over the full range
of compositions from 0 to 1.
And you can see that you have a
behavior in which the enthalpy
of mixing is negative.
OK, so meaning
that the substance
that when you mix the substance,
you have an exothermic reaction.
It's not really a reaction, but
it's a physical chemical effect,
which releases heat.
So in other words, you have to--
if you want to return to mutual
equilibrium with the reservoir,
you have to cool down
after the mixing.
You have to cool
down by this amount.
And that cooling
measures is exactly--
so we-- that's how
with the calorimeter,
you can measure that cooling,
and therefore this delta H.
You can also do
similar measurements
for the volume of mixing.
And here, I sketched the--
yeah, I think this line
should be long a little lower
here to the 0 level.
And I sketched--
this is just to show
that it's the volume of
mixing is not always positive.
It can be positive,
it can be negative,
it can be positive in one
range and become negative
in the other range,
depending on the composition.
And it all depends on what
kind of molecules you have,
and how the molecules
interact with each other.
And as you can see,
these two references
where you may want to take a
look to see experimental data,
and how they're treated, date
back to at least 40 years ago.
OK, now, this slide is
also just a parenthetical.
It just says, all right.
So we have seen
that in practice,
with those measurements, we can
infer the values of the chemical
potentials, and therefore
the partial properties.
So the question that we address
in this slide is, can we--
is the meaning of
partial that we
use in partial properties the
same as the meaning of partial
as we use in partial pressures?
And the answer is no because
the definition is different.
However, you can somehow
relate partial properties
in terms of partial pressures.
And here, here is
the way of doing it.
It's just a matter of writing
the chemical potential,
as we see here.
Again, as a function, as it
is of the partial pressure.
So if you take the
differential of this relation
here, which defines
the partial pressure,
and then remember that the
derivatives of the partial--
of the chemical potential
are the partial properties,
then that is where that
relation comes about.
And here are the details.
So if you like to
take derivatives,
this is how you can practice it.
So I'm not going to
explain the details here.
At this stage, we need
to recall something
about what happens
when molecules
come close to one another.
And the Lennard-Jones
model gives you
the potential energy
of the interaction
between two molecules.
So suppose I have one
molecule and I stay in--
and I sit on that molecule
on the reference frame that
moves with that
molecule, and I see
another molecule approaching.
The Lennard-Jones model is a
pair-interaction kind of model.
It looks just what happens
between one molecule
and the other, not the fact--
it doesn't apply well if you
have to consider also the fact
that this molecule may
also, at the same time,
be interacting with a third
and maybe a fourth molecule,
which of course, is
important in liquids.
But OK, so here's the idea.
I'm sitting on that
molecule, and I see
another molecule approaching.
Now, because of the
electronic structure
of atoms and molecules,
the electrons
that are negatively
charged, yes,
are attracted by the nucleus
or the nuclei of the molecule,
or the atom.
But as they approach
other molecules,
they are also a bit attracted by
the nucleus of the other atom.
And that produces
these so-called van
der Waals attractive forces.
So the potential
going negative--
so if this is the
potential, remember
that I can calculate
the force by taking
the derivative of the
potential with respect
to distance minus sine.
So this force is a vector.
And ir is the vector that
points in the direction outward,
so further from the
molecule I am sitting on.
So it's like on
this axis, isobar
is the unit vector
in the r direction,
in the right direction.
All right.
So the usefulness of
having a potential
is that then, you
can calculate forces
by taking the derivative
of the potential.
And as you see,
here is the force--
if the force is negative.
it means that
the-- its direction
is in the opposite sign of the
unit vector in the r direction.
So it points left.
So it's attractive.
So and up to this point,
which is about here,
the derivative is--
the derivative of v is positive.
So the force is negative.
And yeah.
Yeah, OK, up to this
point, where it is 0,
we get to the minimum,
it's attractive.
And from this point on,
it becomes repulsive.
The force becomes positive.
That repulsion is
due to the fact
that now, the nuclei, which
are positively charged,
begin to fill the positive
charge of the nuclei
of the particle I'm sitting on.
And therefore, that repels.
OK, so most of the
times, molecules
are running around in
their Brownian motion.
So in which they have
some kinetic energy
due to the velocity they have.
And they have also
this potential energy.
Some of that kinetic energy gets
transformed in potential energy.
Or actually when the
molecule approaches and gets
an attractive force, it
gains kinetic energy.
So it's accelerated
towards the particles.
So if the molecule is
coming from the right
and it's approaching,
it's accelerated
towards the molecules
I'm sitting in.
But then, all of a sudden, it
finds also a repulsive force.
So that's decelerating.
Of course, if the kinetic--
if the kinetic energy is enough,
this molecule can go and hit.
So make a collision.
Eventually, it will
make a collision
because the force is going
to become very large.
And the repulsive force
becomes very large.
And therefore, the particle
is pushed away back.
That's a collision.
It's like a soft collision,
but it's a collision.
An even simpler model of this
would be the so-called hard
sphere model, in which the
potential is-- would be like--
OK.
OK, will be like this.
A function, so v,
is a function which
goes to infinite,
to its infinite
at this point, which is 1.
It's the distance-- 1 is
because we're normalizing these
to the diameter of these
molecules, of these spheres,
assuming they're equal.
Otherwise, it would be like
the-- have to normalize
to the average--
it's the sum of the radii
of the two molecules.
And it's 0 here.
So the hard sphere model
assumes no attractive force
until the sphere hits like
in a billiard ball situation.
It hits the other
molecule and it
gets repelled by some elastic
condition-- elastic collision.
OK, let's return to this
case here and now consider
two important regimes.
One regime is the ideal
gas, the gas regime.
So it's true that the
molecules of the gas
very often, billions of
collisions per second, we--
maybe we'll have a slide later
on that does that calculation,
do have experienced collisions.
So these molecules do get
to feel this potential when
they approach the other
molecules and have a collision.
That happens very often.
But if you look up, if
you make an average,
a time average, of how much
time this molecule spends
in this area, where the
Lennard-Jones potential is
negative, is very small.
Most of the times, on average,
the particles are far apart.
And therefore, on average,
they feel zero potential.
See, this is why when you try
to measure the properties,
you're actually measuring
the properties on average,
because remember that somehow,
the state of your system
is the probability
distribution of things.
For example, here is the
probability distribution
of finding the particle at
these various distances.
And that probability
for a gas is--
has this very small tail
here, and it peaks away.
So most of the
times, the particles
are far away from each
other even though they
experience a lot of collisions.
But that means that
when you're calculating
the stable equilibrium
properties,
therefore, the average
time average properties,
this potential is irrelevant.
And that is what allows
you to, for example,
use the hard sphere
model because that's
totally equivalent if
the particles live far
away on average and the
details of the potential
of their interaction
when they are close
is not important, well, those
details, you can forget.
They don't enter
into determining
the properties of the mixtures.
So much that in the
ideal gas, and also,
we will hopefully have a slide
also on this, the ideal gas,
this relation here that
the volume is rt over p,
you can derive for a
particle, a single particle,
in a box, which is a
nice illustration also
of that's why I will
have a slide on this.
But in other words, this--
here in this context
is just to say that the
properties of an ideal gas, so
the origin of this ideal
gas equation of state
comes from the single particle
because the properties
of stable equilibrium
in this regime
are those of particles that
leave on average by themselves.
They don't feel the effects
of the other particles.
There is another case also,
which is the liquid case.
We will return to the liquid
in a while, maybe today.
But what's important is that
instead, the liquid particles
live very close to one another.
They live near this minimum.
So for them, this potential
is more important.
This-- the Lennard-Jones
potential formula can be
written--
is written in two
different ways here.
One is in terms of
the actual distance,
and one is in terms of
the distance normalized
to this minimum to the distance
at which the minimum occurs.
Sigma, as I already said, is--
r is normalized here to sigma.
So it's 1 at the
distance where it
is equal to the diameter
of the two particles.
So where the particles
are colliding.
And here, we also in the
plot normalized the potential
to epsilon.
And epsilon is the
depth of this well here.
So it goes to minus 1.
So stronger
interactions will have--
would be characterized by
stronger values of this epsilon.
OK, so with this
introduction, let's
consider a first
ideal behavior, which
we will call Gibbs-Dalton
ideal behavior,
and which will be a very
good approximation for gases
in the gas phase,
because in practice, we
will assume that not only
particles of the same kind
like you would have
in a pure substance,
but also particles of different
kind like we have in a mixture,
they also live on average
far away from one another.
And therefore, we can
neglect the effect
of their intermolecular
interactions.
OK, all right.
Formally, this is
how the story goes.
We will first define
ideal behavior.
And just so this will
be our-- this will be
the final result of this slide.
And the motivation is
that of this definition
that we are going to
do here is that we
will find that under
this approximation,
or in this limit on this--
when these
assumptions are valid,
then we obtain a
famous result, which
is the Dalton law of
additive partial pressures.
So the pressure
of the mixture is
going to be equal to the
sum of the partial pressures
of the constituents
of the mixture.
But in general,
that is not true.
Not-- I mean, this is not
true for a non-ideal mixture.
So the derivation
goes as follows.
We start from the Euler relation
written for the mixture.
We write also the Euler relation
for the pure components.
And when-- and here,
I'm going to write it
for the pure components
at just on the other side
of the semi-permeable
membrane so they
are in at the same
temperature of the mixture,
but at the partial pressure.
OK, so this uii here, I'm not
writing the explicit dependence,
but I'm doing it here,
are to be evaluated
at t and partial pressure.
Then I take these
individual pure constituent
Euler relations, we multiply--
I multiply them by the amount ni
with which that constituent is
present in the mixture and
sum over all components.
And then I take this
summation, subtract it
from the Euler relation for the
mixture, and here is the result.
So you can still identify
here the Euler relation
for the mixture is
given by this term.
This ts minus pv plus mu i ni.
And what I subtracted is the
summation of the ni's with which
that are the amounts
in the mixture
times the single component,
pure component, Euler relation.
uii minus tsii plus pii
vii and plus the mus.
Actually, there's a
mistake here because there
shouldn't be a summation here.
This is, again, a
cut-and-paste problem.
This should be-- I hope I'll
remember all these things
to correct in the view graphs.
Yeah, so for the pure
component, there's only one.
And so there is no summation.
OK, now, look at these
elements of the last summation.
They are identically 0
because of the condition
for mutual equilibrium
that the chemical potential
of component i in the mixture is
equal to the chemical potential
of the pure component
when evaluated
at the partial pressure.
So these are 0.
And then I get a relation here,
which contains the pressure
and contains the
partial pressures,
because after all, what
we wanted to see here is,
is there a relation between
pressure and partial pressures?
And here is the result.
So I put in evidence,
I solve this expression
for the total pressure,
and here is how it depends
on the partial pressures.
That's all over.
However, if I make these three
assumptions, you see this?
The first assumption kills
these terms in parentheses.
The second assumption
kills this other term.
The third assumption, and note
here that this is not a mistake,
here, there is no
summation sign.
So if this holds, then
we'll discuss what it means.
But if this holds, it means
that inside this summation,
every time I see ni times
vii, I can put capital V,
which doesn't depend on i.
It doesn't have a subscript.
So it goes outside
of the summation
and it cancels with the
V in the denominator.
And then what I'm left
with in the summation
is just the partial pressure.
So I finally get that the
pressure, if these three
assumptions are together,
all holding, the pressure
is equal to the sum of
the partial pressures.
And this is Dalton's law.
Let's see how we could
interpret those conditions that
define the ideal
Gibbs-Dalton behavior.
Essentially, it says that
I can see the mixture,
or at least I can model the
properties of the mixture,
as the model, as the properties
of a composite system in which I
have the pure components leaving
each one in the same volume
of the mixture, so
boxes of the same size,
at the same temperature and
at the partial pressure.
OK, then in these conditions,
this is the specific--
they have a specific
energy since they are pure.
For example, this
is component, say,
component i as a
specific energy, which
is u double i evaluated
at the t and p
because here it is at
the partial pressure.
The same for the entropy.
And now, if I use the fact
that energy and entropy are
additive properties, the energy
of this one is n1 times u11.
And so I sum up ni times uii.
And that gives me
the properties,
the property of the mixture.
So sum of ni times uii.
So that's-- this last equation
is the defining equation
for ideal Gibbs-Dalton behavior.
The first one here
I have added also
the general expression,
which is valid always,
which gives the property in
terms of the partial properties.
It's the same for the entropy.
So it's additive.
So I can view this.
And instead-- and here, I've
used the fact that each--
you see here, I could also
write the specific volume
of the constituent,
the partial pressure.
And the fact that it--
that in the same amount of
the mixture, it occupies,
the same volume of the mixture
is the sort of interpretation
of this formula here.
It also goes together
with the idea
that in the gas limit,
when molecules live
far apart from one another in
either this or the Lennard-Jones
kind of potential, if they're
on average, they live here.
Essentially, they stay and they
occupy the volume of the mixture
if--
as if they were by themselves,
each molecule by itself.
And that's why we have--
they obey the ideal
gas law, which
is valid for the single
molecule in a box
even if I have many box--
many particles In that box.
But it is as if each one
uses the box by itself.
It doesn't recognize on average,
the presence of the other,
even though it does continuously
collide with the other.
But the time that it takes--
that the collision--
and so that--
it lasts.
The time that the
collision lasts
is very short with respect
to the rest of the time
that the particle
moves freely in space
before encountering the other
molecule for the next collision.
So that's the ideal
Gibbs-Dalton behavior.
And if we apply
it now, we haven't
assumed yet the ideal gas.
So now, if we in
addition to those,
we also assume that each
pure substance behaves
as an ideal gas, so
it obeys the equation
of state of an ideal gas in
the full range of pressures
from the partial pressure to the
total pressure of the mixture,
I shouldn't call it total, to
the pressure of the mixture.
So I can write the
equation of state
for the gas pv equals rt
both at partial pressure
and at the pressure
of the mixture.
Then you see from assumption
three, which is this,
I substitute this,
obtain this result.
So I obtain the partial
pressure written this way.
Now, I'm using what we proved
in the Gibbs-Dalton theorem,
about the Dalton law that
the pressure of the mixture
is the sum of the
partial pressures.
So take the sum of
these ones, see rt and v
do not have subscripts, so
they go out of the summation.
I'm left with the
sum of the n's,
which is just the total n of
the particles in the mixture.
So here, what do I got?
What do I get?
That pv equals nrt.
So it means that also, the
mixture behaves as an ideal gas.
So what this proves is that
an ideal Gibbs-Dalton mixture
of ideal gases
obeys the equation
of state of an ideal gas.
So it is an ideal gas itself.
And the other
important result is
that if you extract
rt over v from here,
you see that you can write
it as partial pressure
over the amount.
And rt over v from
here, it's the pressure
over the total amount.
So that's essentially
you combine these two
and you obtain that the
ratio of the partial pressure
to the total pressure
is equal to the ratio
of the individual amount
with the total amount, which
is the mole fraction.
In other words, the
partial pressure
is given by the mole
fraction of that constituents
times the pressure
of the mixture.
And this relation, if we
put it in this relation
that we have derived
before, so pii over p
becomes in the limit of
a Gibbs-Dalton mixture.
That is the mole fraction.
So this is rt, the logarithm
of the mole fraction.
And this is a very
important relation.
It gives the chemical
potential of one constituent
in the mixture.
In terms of the chemical
potential that it has,
when it is a pure substance,
at the same temperature
and pressure of the mixture.
Plus rt, the log of
its mole fraction,
of the mole fraction with which
it appears in the mixture.
So it doesn't depend on
other things of the mixture.
For example, what are the other
components, or how many they
are except that all we need
is to know what fraction
our component is
occupies in the mixture.
OK, the first few
lines of this slide
are just a cut and
paste from the previous.
But here, we add
some other items.
For example, we
compute the entropy--
the partial entropy of the
component in the mixture,
which as you remember,
is this derivative.
It is equal to the
pure component entropy
plus a term that in--
when we define the entropy of
mixing at the beginning today,
this is delta si mix.
But if we-- since now,
for this ideal gas
mixture of ideal gases,
we have the expression
for the chemical potential
in terms of explicitly
here, taking the derivative
with respect to t,
we see leaves just r
times the log of y.
And since there is a minus sign
here, this is minus r log of y.
So essentially, these and we'll
return to this in a later,
but this says that the
entropy of isothermal--
isothermobaric mixing
of that molecule is--
of that molecule is equal
to minus r log of y.
And this is also equal to the
pure component entropy evaluated
at pii.
This is because you
remember for a gas,
for an ideal gas, if I evaluate
the difference in the entropy
a different temperature and
pressure, OK, this is equal to--
and this is the perfect--
let's suppose it's
a perfect gas.
It's t2 over t1 minus
r log p2 over p1.
So in this relation here,
we have s evaluated at p.
p, all right, let's say p.
pii minus s evaluated at p.
Same temperature.
So this doesn't give
any contribution.
So I'm left with minus
r log of pii over p.
But that's in our limit of ideal
mixture is the mole fraction.
So hopefully, what I've
written on the board
is this relation here.
That's to justify
this equal sign.
We can also compute
the partial volume,
taking the derivative of
this with respect to p
and you see that since this
last term doesn't have pressure,
I just pick up something
from the derivative
of the chemical potential
of the pure component.
And that's the specific volume.
So here, we see that there
is no volume of mixing.
There is no iso--
the delta-- essentially, we
are proving that delta vi mix
for a Gibbs-Dalton
mixture of ideal gases
and so on is equal to 0.
Up here, we prove that
this is equal to delta si
mix for a Gibbs-Dalton
mixture of ideal gases.
I should write it
because otherwise--
OK, the same for the enthalpy.
Remember that derivative that I
emphasized this morning earlier,
if I take the expression for the
chemical potential divided by t
and take the derivative with
respect to t to 1 over t,
OK, well, if I
divide this by t, it
becomes independent
of temperature.
So when I take the
derivative with respect
to any function of temperature,
it doesn't contribute anything.
So that means that
the enthalpy--
the partial enthalpy
is related just
to the specific enthalpy of
the gas, which here also, I
removed the temperature,
the pressure
dependence, because
for an ideal gas,
the enthalpy depends
only on temperature.
And similarly for the--
so that also proves that
also delta h mix equals 0.
And remember what
these properties are.
These are the things
that I measure
when I add a little bit of
a substance to my mixture.
If I do it with an ideal mixture
of ideal gases, those are 0.
We can also prove for a gas
for this kind of mixture,
the so-called Amagat law
of additive volumes, which
can be interpreted this way.
Suppose I take my
pure components
that you remember from when we
interpreted the mixture before,
if they are at the
partial pressure,
they occupy the entire
volume of the mixture.
But if I squeeze them from the
partial pressure to the pressure
of the mixture, they are going
to occupy a volume, which
is called the proper volume, v
prime, which see, this is not--
So this is the
volume they occupy
at the same temperature
and pressure of the mixture
when pure.
And I do the same
for all of them.
So they are all squeezed at the
same pressure of the mixture.
Well, it turns out that
the sum of these volumes
is equal to the
volume of the mixture.
OK, and that is Amagat's
law of additive volumes.
OK, so now, let's
apply for example,
for an important example,
what we have seen.
So we want to compute
the so-called--
this bottom line
here is the formula
that we call the entropy of
spontaneous mixing, which
is actually going to be
an isothermobaric mix.
So the idea here
is that we start
with a container,
which is isolated
so it doesn't experience any--
there is no heat bath, no
thermal reservoir, no contact
with thermal reservoirs.
It's just isolated.
And I have my r constituents
all in mutual equilibrium
at the same temperature
and pressure
because these partitions that
separate them are movable,
and therefore allow exchanges
of volume and energy.
So the conditions for
mutual equilibrium
is equality of temperature
and equality of pressure.
Then, I make those partitions,
those moving partitions,
disappear.
As you know, since we are
within the simple system model,
taking the partition away
doesn't change the properties
of any of the properties.
And the moment I
do that removal,
the particles are
still separated.
So the particles, it's
which start from here.
And my system is the
system with the partitions.
When I remove the partitions,
the stable equilibrium state,
and the new system because I've
changed the internal structure,
it has a new curve for the
stable equilibrium states.
And the moment I have
removed the partitions
and the properties haven't
changed, this state here,
which is--
which was a stable equilibrium
state with the partitions,
becomes a non-equilibrium state
with respect to the system
without partitions.
And the system will tend
to evolve spontaneously
towards a new equilibrium, which
is going to be the mixture.
The particles will mix.
And each one of
them, if you think
in terms of the single
particle contribution,
each particle here was
squeezed to a small volume.
And now, it sees the
entire volume available.
So it expands.
And the same for the particles
here, and the same for
particles there.
So each one experiences
a spontaneous expansion.
It's like if you take
the single particle view,
so say particle one,
and here, I have vacuum,
OK, I remove the
partition and the particle
now fills the entire volume
and fills the entire volume.
There is no more vacuum,
because at the beginning,
I had zero probability of
finding my particles here,
and probability 1
of finding it there.
When I remove the partition,
the particle is still one.
But now, I have an
even probability
of finding it everywhere.
OK, so for the moment,
we want to describe
that spontaneous process.
And so we want to
analyze our process here.
We have a final state
and an initial state.
And the tools are, as
usual, the energy balance
and the entropy balance.
Plus the auxiliary
balances that are
balanced for the volume
balance for the amounts
of the constituents.
So I need to write the various
ingredients of those balance
equations, which are the
expressions for the energy,
the volume, and the entropy
in the initial state,
and in the final state.
I've called this
final state b prime.
And I call that final
temperature t prime and pressure
p prime.
For the initial
state, things are
easy because the
components are separate.
So these are-- this
is just a composite
of separate substances.
We know how to compute
properties of pure substances.
And here in particular, they
are ideal gases, even simpler.
And so we simply have
to use additivity
for energy, for
volume, and for entropy
and sum up the energy
of each one of them.
Since u is the specific energy,
the energy of this system
is obtained by the specific
energy times the amount.
And then I sum, and
that's the additivity.
And the same for volume,
the same for entropy.
In the final state,
in the final state,
things are not as simple
because it's a mixture.
So we have to take a model
for mixture behavior.
So here, we are going to
adopt the Gibbs-Dalton--
ideal Gibbs-Dalton mixture
model for this state.
Therefore, the energy
for the mixture
is equal to the sum
weighted by the amounts
of the specific properties of
the pure components evaluated
at the temperature and
the partial pressure.
So here in principle, I
should have written comma pii.
But I didn't because I
remember that for an ideal gas,
the energy is a function
only of temperature.
So that dependence isn't
there because if you remember,
the u is equal to cvdt.
And for an ideal gas, there is
nothing, no pressure dependence.
And here, we are
talking about something
that holds for each of
the pure substances.
Then, we can use
the relation for--
this is Amagat's
relation, or you
can use, in any case,
the equation of state.
And we already proved that v
is equal to that the mixture
of ideal gases under
the Gibbs-Dalton model
behaves itself as an ideal gas.
So there is the relation,
equation of state pv
equals nrt for the
entire mixture here.
And that's what we use here.
And then for the
entropy, the entropy
is the sum of the entropies of
the specific entropies evaluated
at the partial pressures.
Now, the entropy does
depend on pressure.
So I did leave the
partial pressure
that the components
have in the final state.
So these are just
the ingredients
of the balance equations.
Now, I make the
balanced equation.
So the balanced
equation, when the system
is completely isolated is
that the energy is conserved.
So u final minus u
initial is equal to 0.
So I have u final, I have
u initial, I subtract them.
I can put this under
the same summation.
Then, I remember
this equation here.
And so for each of
the constituents,
I can write that
the integrate from t
to t prime, this difference, so
this is the integral from t to t
prime of cv.
And here, there
should be a cvii.
OK, OK.
So this integral has
to be equal to 0.
Now, when can that
be equal to 0?
Now, here, we have to
remember a few things,
that for each pure substance,
the specific heats are
non-negative, are
greater than 0.
We proved it because they are
related to the second derivative
of the fundamental relations.
They are related to
this concavity here.
So we have an integral
of positive quantities,
of a positive function,
weighted and then
multiplied by positive numbers
because the amounts can only
be positive, of course.
It cannot be a negative amount.
So you can view
this as an integral
of a function, an
integral from, say,
x1 to x2 of a function
that has to be equal to 0,
while this function is positive.
So here is a function,
positive, and the integral
is equal to this
area from x1 to x2.
So if the function is positive
and I want the integral to be 0,
the only way is that the
interval of integration
must be 0.
So that implies that this
integral is equal to 0 only
when x2 is equal to x1.
So that proves that
the final temperature
must be equal to the
initial temperature.
We've no need to make
any assumptions of what
these functions
are, whether they
are functions of whether
they are constant or not.
They can be functions, arbitrary
functions of temperature,
still get the same result.
Then, if I make the volume
balance equation, here
is another mistake,
this is a v, not a u.
So the final volume, since we
are in the same overall box,
final volume is equal
to initial volume.
So v-- these two are equal.
If I look at this
relation here, it
says that if I put them
equal, it says that t over p
is equal to t
prime over p prime.
So that means that
if we just prove
that t prime is equal to t,
so the final temperature is
equal to the initial,
the volume balance
implies that also
the final pressure is
equal to the initial.
So spontaneous mixing with these
conditions is isothermobaric.
Different story is for
the entropy balance.
The entropy balance is written
here with another little mistake
because this should be a
capital S. So the final entropy
minus the initial entropy.
There are no interactions.
So there is no entropy transfer.
There are no heat interactions.
But there can be entropy
produced by irreversibility.
So we rewrite this.
So S here is equal
to SB minus SA.
And I have the terms here.
So I substitute.
Now, I realize that
this we can also write--
well, actually, it's
this expression here.
I have to--
I don't have to re-prove it.
It's written here.
This difference is
equal to minus r log
y, which is also is
interpreted as the entropy
of isothermobaric mixing.
And therefore, the-- if I take
r, the minus sign, outside
of the summation, I take
also the total amount
out of the summation.
Then, I'm left inside with the
mole fraction times the log
of the mole fraction.
Now, at first, at first sight,
one would be worried about
the minus sign because we
know that the entropy produced
by irreversibility cannot be
negative, must be positive.
But if you look at
this function y log
y, the function in the
interval between 0 and 1,
the function y log y
does something like that.
Versus y.
So it's negative.
So minus y log y is positive.
And we are safe.
That means for any reasonable,
in other words, possible values
of the mole fractions,
which of course can go only
between 0 and 1, that
function is non-negative.
But it also says that there
is entropy production.
So the process is
irreversible as we
have anticipated by
looking at the energy
versus entropy graphs.
And this is called
the entropy of mixing.
Now, so if I look at that
graph, immediately, I also
realize that I have--
that I could have done better.
In other words, we could have
done the mixing reversibly
because if I-- if instead of
going this way, I go this way,
I do not generate entropy.
And I extract some work.
So this is what we call
the adiabatic availability
of the state that is
achieved the moment I
remove the partition.
That non-equilibrium state
has adiabatic availability
if I am quick enough,
or smart enough,
to do whatever needs to be done.
And we'll see how we
could do it in a moment.
We could extract some work.
So here is the
calculation of that,
the adiabatic availability.
So now, the final state,
OK, what we just derived
is that if you--
if we mix this way,
the final state is the same
temperature and pressure.
Clearly, if we go down and we
have extracted some energy,
the final state here will have
a smaller temperature, which
we call it t double prime.
And how do we measure it?
How do we do the computation?
Well, we start-- the
previous computation,
we started from
the energy balance
setting that final energy
is equal to initial energy.
That determines the temperature.
Now, we start from
the entropy balance
because for a reversible
process because we
want to extract the
adiabatic availability,
so that's a reversible
weight process.
The entropy stays constant.
We apply equality of
final and initial entropy.
And so we start from
the entropy balance.
Yeah, here is the
entropy balance.
S final minus S
initial equals 0.
So we write it this way
with the double primes.
And then this difference
here, we can--
yeah, it's evaluated.
It's evaluated in this line
because, OK, t double prime
is the final temperature
that we have.
p double prime double I
is the partial pressure
that the components will
have in that new final state.
So that partial
pressure is going
to be equal to
the mole fraction.
So that partial pressure will
be equal to the mole fraction
times the final
pressure p double prime.
But if we remember, if
we remember the question
of if we look at the volume
balance, which is written here,
p double prime over t double
prime is equal to p over t.
So I can think of p double
prime, p double prime,
as what is it?
p over t.
As p times t double
prime over t.
And that's why I am
writing this here.
Then I apply the relation
for how the entropy depends
on temperature and pressure.
Here, we also have a
temperature dependence.
So we also have the
cp log contribution
of the ratio of temperatures
minus r, the log
of the ratio of the pressures.
OK, then I can
split this logarithm
as being the logarithm
of the product
is going to be the
sum of the logarithms.
So I take the
minus r log y here.
And then I combine the
log of t double prime
that appears from this
part and with that part.
It gets multiplied
by cv minus r,
but by the Moire
relation that's cv.
OK, so we finally
have this expression.
We can put it in
the entropy balance.
Now, I see here that I could
define an average-specific heat
at constant volume of the
mixture as being the weighted
as being this summation here.
And then I recognize this final
term, which is very close.
I mean, it's exactly what we
call the entropy of mixing.
But in any case, by setting--
since this has to be equal
to 0 by the entropy balance,
this gives me an expression way
to calculate t double prime,
the final temperature.
And this is the result. Now, the
fact that these functions are
negative, so e to a negative
number is less than 1,
shows that, of course,
as we expected,
the final temperature
will be less
than the initial temperature.
And now that we have
the final temperature,
we can perform the
energy balance.
Now, the energy balance here,
since the system is not isolated
anymore, because we have lifted
the weight in a weight process,
we have extracted the
adiabatic availability.
So the energy
given to the weight
is equal to the difference
between the initial
and the final energy.
So by substituting these
ingredients that we calculated
up there and using the
same-- the specific heat
at constant volume, and then
the fact that the summation
we defined as sort of an average
mixing mixture, specific heat
at constant volume.
And we substitute
t double prime.
And you compute the value for
the adiabatic availability.
So we see that this
represents this work.
Just to show you how we could
actually do it with a picture,
so we conclude, we
have one minute.
How can we do that?
Can we actually
separate a mixture?
Remember, the problem here
with the single particle,
if I have a single particle
there, and I have vacuum,
and I have this-- and instead
of removing the piston,
I can just have it move
rightward while connected
through a pulley to a weight.
And the pressure of the particle
will push it to the right.
Therefore, the particle
will do work and lift.
And similarly, if I
have this other particle
on the other different
particle on the other side,
say, suppose I have a
particle of different kind
that is confined,
that's separated,
and it's on the other side.
Also here, I can do
the same and have
the pressure of the
particle, or the particles.
Doesn't really matter because
each one acts by itself.
So that pulls this this way.
And when you have the
presence of both particles,
you have to do it
more carefully.
Instead of having an
impermeable piston,
you have to use semi-permeable
membranes so that when this one
moves to the right, it will--
so this one allows
the black particles
to freely move in and out.
And then it fills only the
pressure of the gray particles
until you move to the right.
And this other
membrane, instead, is--
allows the gray particles
through, and instead,
fills the pressure of
the black particles.
OK, so when you're done, and
if you've done it reversibly,
you have extracted this
adiabatic availability.
So I think we have
to stop here today.